<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<missing/>
<errors>
 <para id="21">
  <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">
   He was beloved not for any essential ability but for those unforgettable digressions of his, when he would remove his glasses to beam at the past while massaging the lenses of the present.
  </se>
  <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">
   Его любили не за какие-то особые дарования, но за незабываемые отступления, когда он снимал очки, чтобы улыбнуться прошлому, массируя тем временем линзы настоящего.
  </se>
 </para>
 <para id="22">
  <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">
   Nostalgic excursions in broken English.
  </se>
  <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">
   Ностальгические отступления на ломанном английском.
  </se>
 </para>
 <para id="23">
  <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">
   Autobiographical titbits.
  </se>
  <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">
   Лакомые крохи автобиографии.
  </se>
 </para>
 <para id="27">
  <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">
   "Nothing to declare?" "Nothing."
  </se>
  <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">
   "Что-то для декларации?"
  </se>
 </para>
 <para id="47">
  <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">
   Pnin, it should be particularly stressed, was anything but the type of that good-natured German platitude of last century, der zerstreute Professor. On the contrary, he was perhaps too wary, too persistently on the look-out for diabolical pitfalls, too painfully on the alert lest his erratic surroundings (unpredictable America) inveigle him into some bit of preposterous oversight.
  </se>
  <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">
   Пнин, это стоит подчеркнуть особо, вовсе не был типичным образчиком благонамеренной немецкой пошлости прошлого века, der zerstreute Professor1. Напротив, он был, возможно, чересчур осторожен, слишком усерден в выискивании дьявольских ловушек, слишком бдителен, ибо опасался, что окружающий беспорядок (непредсказуемая Америка!) подтолкнет его к совершению какого-нибудь дурацкого промаха.
  </se>
 </para>
 <para id="60">
  <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">
   Except for such not very helpful odds and ends as 'the rest is silence', 'nevermore', 'week-end', 'who's who', and a few ordinary words like' eat', 'street', 'fountain pen', 'gangster', 'Charleston', 'marginal utility', he had had no English at all at the time he left France for the States. Stubbornly he sat down to the task of learning the language of Fenimore Cooper, Edgar Poe, Edison, and thirty-one Presidents.
  </se>
  <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">
   Перебираясь из Франции в Штаты, он вообще не знал английского, не считая всякой малополезной всячины вроде "the rest is silence", "nevermore", "week-end", "who's who"1, да нескольких незатейливых слов наподобие "eat", "street", "fountain pen", "gangster", "Charleston", "marginal utility"2. С усердием приступил он к изучению языка Фенимора Купера, Эдгара По, Эдисона и тридцати одного президента.
  </se>
 </para>
 <para id="61">
  <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">
   In 1941, at the end of one year of study, he was proficient enough to use glibly terms like 'wishful thinking' and 'okey-dokey'. By 1942 he was able to interrupt his narration with the phrase, 'To make a long story short'. By the time Truman entered his second term, Pnin could handle practically any topic: but otherwise progress seemed to have stopped despite all his efforts, and by 1950 his English was still full of flaws.
  </se>
  <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">
   В 1941 году, на исходе первого года обучения, он продвинулся достаточно для того, чтобы бойко пользоваться оборотами вроде "wishful thinking" и "okey-dokey"3. К 1942 году он умел уже прервать свой рассказ фразой "To make a long story short"4. Ко времени избрания Трумэна на второй срок Пнин мог управиться с любой темой, однако дальнейшее продвижение застопорилось, несмотря на все его старания, и к 1950 году его английский по-прежнему был полон огрехов.
  </se>
 </para>
 <para id="71">
  <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">
   Pnin's worried eye would be bound to lose its bearings. Therefore he preferred reading his lectures, his gaze glued to his text, in a slow, monotonous baritone that seemed to climb one of those interminable flights of stairs used by people who dread elevators.
  </se>
  <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">
   Поэтому он предпочитал читать свои лекции, влипая глазами в текст, - медленным, монотонным баритоном, казалось, карабкавшимся вверх по одной из тех нескончаемых лестниц, которыми пользуются боящиеся лифта люди.
  </se>
 </para>
 <para id="74">
  <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">
   He was in a Pninian quandary.
  </se>
  <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">
   Он пребывал в состоянии пнинианского затруднения.
  </se>
 </para>
 <para id="84">
  <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">
   'Important lecture!' cried Pnin.
  </se>
  <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">
   - Важная лекция! - возопил Пнин.
  </se>
 </para>
 <para id="85">
  <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">
   'What to do?
  </se>
  <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">
   - Что делать?
  </se>
 </para>
</errors>